Hello again.
In this video, we are going to look at the lock_guard class in the standard library. This solves one
of the problems with mutexes.
The problem is that if an exception is thrown in the critical region, the mutex is left locked.
So let's have a look at that.
So this is the code that we had before. When the thread goes into the loop, it looks the mutex.
It can display its output without having any other thread interfere with this, and then it unlocks
the mutex, which will allow some other thread to run.
So what happens if we throw an exception in here?
Right.
Well, that is not very good!
The program has been terminated.
So we can see that one thread has managed to do one line of output.
What has happened is that the first thread to run has gone into the loop. It has locked its mutex,
it has done its output, and then the exception is thrown.
When that happens, the destructors are called for all the objects in the scope.
Well, there are not really any, except for the variable i, I suppose. And then the thread will jump out
of the loop and look for an exception handler.
There aren't any.
So the thread is terminated and that causes the entire program to terminate.
So let's put in an exception handler.
Okay, well, the program is still running, but it is not doing very much.
So what happened this time, was that the first thread to run locked the mutex. It did some output, the exception
was thrown, the thread that jumped into the catch handler.
The problem is that the threat did not call unlock, so this mutex is still locked and all the threads
which are waiting for a lock on that mutex are going to be waiting forever.
The program is deadlocked because nothing can happen until this thread unlocks the mutex.
But this thread has stopped running, so it cannot unlock the mutex.
Okay, so the obvious way to do this is to unlock the mutex in the catch handler.
So let's see what effect that has.
OK, so the program is now run and successfully completed - or some values of "successfully" anyway!
Each thread has run once.
The first thread to run locks the mutex and prints some output, then the exception is thrown and in the exception
handler, it unlocks the mutex. Then the next thread can run and the same thing happens again.
That throws an exception and unlocks the mutex.
Then the third thread runs and - same problem again.
We only get one output because the handler is outside the loop. So we could move the handler inside
the loop.
(Now let's see what happens)
OK, so each thread has been able to execute all the outputs in its loop, and then if we remove this
print statement, then we should get what looks like a normal output.
Yes, there we go.
OK, so we have solved the problem.
So the problem again, the mutex is not unlocked if an exception is thrown.
All the threads which are waiting to acquire the lock will be blocked.
main() is joined on the blocked threads.
So main() is going to be blocked as well, so the whole program is deadlocked.
So this is a problem with the mutex. Whenever we call lock(), we must put in a corresponding call to
unlock(), either in the code or an exception handler.
If we have code which has many different return paths, then they all have to have an unlock() and we have
to be careful not to unlock twice.
So this is why programmers do not normally use the mutex directly.
There are some classes in the standard library which we can use to wrap the mutex, and these follow the
RAII idiom for managing resources, "Resource Allocation Is Initialization", which means that we allocate
the resource in the constructor and we release it in the destructor.
Some examples you may have met are the fstream for managing files, unique_ptr for managing allocated
memory.
In both cases, the file is opened in the constructor and closed in the destructor.
The memory is allocated by the unique_ptr constructor and released in the destructor.
In this case, the resource that the class manages is a lock on a mutex.
The constructor will take the mutex object as its argument and it will lock it and the destructor will
unlock it.
If we create an object of one of these classes as a local variable, that means that the mutex will
be automatically unlocked when the object goes out of scope.
If an exception is thrown,
Or you have 57 different return paths from your thread function and someone adds a 58th, then the
mutex will always be unlocked.
The first wrapper class we are going to look at is lock_guard. This is a very basic wrapper class. It only
has two member functions, the constructor and the destructor which lock and unlock the mutex. We need
to give the type of the mutex as a parameter to the lock_guard, unless we're using C++ 17, in which
case the compiler can work it out.
So we just put lock_guard, the name of the variable and the mutex argument.
So we do not need to put an explicit lock() and unlock() calls to the mutex, we just create a lock_guard
instance and we pass the mutex as its argument, and then we do that just before the critical region.
And then when we get to the end of the scope, the local variable will be destroyed.
The destructor is called and that will unlock the mutex.
Let's try this out.
There we are. Lovely!
So when we create the lock_guard instance here, that will lock the mutex and then that will mean that the critical
region can only be executed by this thread, and then the mutex will always be unlocked, even if we
throw an exception...
So there it is.
We do not need to do anything in the exception handler concerning the mutex. When the exception is thrown,
the destructor is called for the lock_guard and that unlocks the mutex.
So the mutex has always been unlocked by the time we get to the catch handler.
So there we are again: when it goes out of scope, the destructor is called and the mutex is unlocked without
any extra work by the programmer. Which is always good news. If you can get the compiler or the library
to do work for you,
that is always a good thing.
There is just one problem with that, actually, if we go back and look at this again, the mutex is
not unlocked until the end of the scope.
So this means that we're locking the mutex while we are sleeping. While we have the lock on the
mutex no other thread can execute this critical section.
So we are basically shutting out all the other threads while we're sleeping.
That is one issue with lock_guard. We will look in the next video at another wrapper which solves that problem.
In C++17, there is a scoped_lock, which is exactly the same. The only difference is it can lock
more than one mutex at the same time.
So we can create a scoped_lock and give it several mutexes and it will lock them.
You notice that we don't give the template parameter here because this is C++17.
The mutexes are always locked in the order that they are given in the constructor call, which is very useful.
We will see later on
that another way to create deadlock is to have threads locking mutexes in different orders.
In the structure, the mutexes will be unlocked and they will be unlocked in the reverse order that
they were locked in.
So this can avoid a lot of problems that can occur when you are dealing with multiple mutexes. Just
one thing to watch out for when you are using scoped_lock.
If you are using it with just one mutex argument, it is easy to forget to put the argument in.
So we get that which is all perfectly fine, but it does not actually lock anything.
So you may get a data race where you were not expecting one.
Okay, that's it for this video.
I will see you next time.
But meanwhile, keep coding!