Hello there.
In this video, we are going to look at deadlock. We have mentioned deadlock a few times, so let's try
and find out exactly what we mean by it.
We say that a thread is deadlocked when it cannot run at all.
There are times when a thread gets interrupted and it cannot run, but then it will wake up again
and it should be able to run.
If a thread is deadlocked, it cannot run at all.
It is completely stuck.
Deadlock often occurs when we have two or more threads waiting for each other.
We have a thread A which is waiting for some other thread B to do something or to finish doing something,
but B cannot finish until it gets something from A.
But B cannot get anything from A because A is not running, because it is waiting for B.
So threads A and B are stuck waiting for each other.
They are both waiting for something which will never happen.
The classic way to demonstrate this is waiting for locks on mutexes.
But there are other situations in which threads can be deadlocked. If thread A is waiting for the results
of some computation that thread B is doing. If it is waiting for a message to be sent by thread B.
Or it could be waiting for thread B to produce some sort of GUI event.
The simplest way to get a deadlock is to have two threads trying to look the same
mutexes in different orders.
So we have the first thread, which looks mutex number one, and the second thread looks mutex number two.
Then this thread wants to lock mutex number two, but it has to wait because that is already locked by
thread two.
Meanwhile, thread two is waiting for a lock on mutex one, which is locked at by thread one.
So thread two cannot run until thread one releases the lock and thread one cannot run until thread
two releases the lock.
So both these threads are stuck waiting for a lock on the mutex.
The code would look like this, so thread one's function will get a lock on mutex one, then try to
get a lock on mutex two.
The other thread will get a lock on mutex number two, then it tries to get a lock on mutex number one. So once
this thread gets the look on mutex number two, it will exit and release the lock on one, which would
allow thread two to run.
But it cannot run yet because the lock has not been released.
But thread two cannot run yet because it is waiting for the lock on mutex one.
So here is the code with some debug information added. So we get the lock on mutex one and then we try
to get the look on mutex two.
In the other thread function, we get the lock on mutex two, then we try to get the lock on mutex
one. And there is a main function, which does nothing very exciting.
Okay, so let's see how that works.
So thread 1 and thread 2 are both trying to lock their mutexes, thread 2 locks mutex number two and thread 1 looks mutex number one, and
then they try to lock the other thread's mutex.
So thread one is waiting for a lock on mutex two, which is already locked by thread two and thread
two is waiting for a lock on mutex one, which is already locked by third one.
So the program is completely deadlocked.
You can see nothing is happening.
I have to press control-C to get out of it.
Now, if we change this, so the the threads get the mutexes in the same order...
Let's see what difference that makes.
So there we are, the program has actually run and completed.
So both sides are trying to lock mutex number one. Thread two gets there first, locks mutex one then
it tries to lock mutex two, then it reaches the end of the thread function and it releases all the locks. Then thread one
can lock mutex number one.
Then it tries to lock mutex two.
There is no one holding a lock in it.
So it can do that and then that can run to completion.
And then the entire program finishes normally.
So here are some guidelines on how to avoid deadlock.
The basic rule is never wait for a thread if there is any chance it could be waiting for your thread
at some point.
And it may not just be a simple two thread situation where A waits for B and B waits for A, you could
have cycles where A waits for B, B waits for C, and C waits for A.
Avoid nested locks. If your thread already has a lock, do not acquire another one, even if it is on a
different mutex.
If you need multiple locks, acquire them in a single operation.
I will show you how to do that in a minute.
If you do need multiple locks and you cannot acquire them in a single operation, then acquire them in
the same order in every thread.
So that was how I avoided deadlock in the code
just then. I made sure that the threads acquire the locks in the same order.
Another piece of advice: do not call code within a critical section unless you know exactly what it
does.
I mean, these are all basically code that could do anything and you do not have control over [them].
These are all types of code in which other people can add locks without you knowing about it, and if
you do not know where the locks are, you do not know what order the locks are going to be taken in, in
different threads.
However, if you do know that the code does not take locks and you know it is not going to be changed,
then that is okay.
Yes, so as we said, we acquire the locks in the same order, but that's not always ideal.
It does rely on the programmer to get it right.
In a simple example like that one, it is not difficult.
But if you have a large program, you may easily lose track of where the locks are taken.
This is not really a viable strategy.
A better option is to use the features provided by the C++ library, which will allow you to lock both
mutexes at the same time. In C++17, we can use a scoped_lock.
So we just have a scoped_lock, which will try to lock both the mutexes in a single call.
And it does not matter what order you put them in.
This will either lock both mutexes or not lock either of them.
So here is that code with a bit more debugging information and some sleeps added. So we have a thread that
calls scoped_lock and another thread that calls scoped_lock with the mutexes in a different order.
Again, the same boring main function.
So this looks OK, both the threads try to look the mutexes, thread two gets there first, then it will
do some work, then it will exit, which will release the mutexes.
Then thread one will lock both mutexes.
It will do some work and it will exit.
So this all works normally.
If you are using C++11 or 14, you can use the lock function to lock both mutexes and then we create
unique_lock instances which will adapt those mutexes.
So these are just ordinary mutexes which happen to be locked.
These objects are unique_lock objects
which will acquire ownership of the lock on the mutex, and we can either manually unlock them
or else they will go out of scope,
and that will cause the lock to be released by the destructor call.
There seem to be a lot of alternative ways of doing things with mutexes, so you can also create
the locks first with the defer_lock argument and then do the call later.
So we have the unique_lock objects which own a lock on the mutexes, but the mutexes do not actually
get locked until later on.
So, again, I put some debugging information into the code.
So we have the lock() call, then we have the unique look with adopt_lock.
Thread two is the same with the mutexes in the reverse order.
So this works more or less the same.
The threads try to lock their mutexes, thread 2 gets there first.
It locks the mutexes, it does some work and then it exits, which releases the mutexes when the destructors
are called on the unique lock objects.
And then thread one can get the locks and do some work and release the mutexes when it goes out of scope.
There are some cases where it is not possible to acquire multiple locks simultaneously because of the
nature of the problem.
In that case, you impose some kind of ordering. For example, you could say that a thread cannot lock a resource,
unless it has already locked something which has a lower identifier and for the identifier, you could
use names or numbers.
The book that I recommend by Anthony Williams, it has the code for a hierarchical mutex that will
implement this.
I have also got a simpler example of that in the workshop for this section.
So when you get to the end of the section and get stuck into the workshop, you will be able to do that
for yourself.
Deadlock is not just about looking mutexes. As we saw earlier, there are some situations, such as waiting
for GUI events, where deadlock can occur.
Generally, it is any situation where threads are waiting for each other, which does not necessarily
require a lock on a mutex.
It can also happen if the threads are calling join() on each other.
And it can also happen if the threads are just stopping and waiting, which we will see how to do later
on.
So if you hold a lock, do not wait for another thread, because that thread may need the lock before
it can do anything. In general, try to avoid waiting for threads.
Because in that case, you will never have a situation where another thread is waiting for your thread.
And when you create a thread, if possible, call join() in the same function where you create the
thread instance.
So, for example, when we create our threads in main(), we should always call join on them in main().
OK, so that's it for this video.
I'll see you next time.
But meanwhile, keep coding!