Hello again. In this video, we are going to talk about livelock. Livelock is related to deadlock.
The difference is that when we have a livelock, all the threads are still active, whereas when we
have deadlock, there are some threads which are no longer active. They are waiting forever.
So when we have deadlock, everything grinds to a halt.
When we have livelock, things are still happening.
One of the most common causes of livelock is badly doing deadlock avoidance. If we think back to the
situation we had before, where we had two threads and each one was waiting to get a lock on a mutex
that was already locked by the other thread, that was deadlock.
We could try and avoid that by saying that instead of waiting for the mutex indefinitely, we are going
to wait with a timeout and then if we cannot get it, we are going to start all over again.
So we're going to release our own lock and then try and get the other thread's.
lock. As an analogy for this, there was a British comedy program in the 1940s, I think, certainly
well before even my time.
And one of the sketches on that was two civil servants trying to go through a door at the same time.
You can imagine the situation.
You have two people walking along a corridor side by side, and then they come to a door which is
only wide enough for one person, and they both try to get in, then they realize they are making a mistake
and they back off and say, "Oh, terribly sorry",
"No, my mistake!"
"No, after you", "No, no after you" and then they wait for the other person, then they both try to go
through it again at the same time. Then they both back off and then they wait, then they go again.
A very British problem!
But livelock is rather like that.
Here is some code which will implement this. So we have the lock on mutex number
one in the thread number one.
And then instead of getting a lock guard, which will wait indefinitely to lock mutex two, we use a try
lock with a timeout.
So this will spend five milliseconds trying to get the lock.
And then at the end of this scope, the lock guard will be destroyed.
The lock on the first mutex will be released.
And then it goes back into the loop and tries again.
So it locks the first mutex and then waits for the timeout for the lock on the second mutex.
And eventually this will succeed and in theory, this should drop out of the loop.
The other thread function is exactly the same, except the mutexes are the other way around.
So first it looks mutex two then it tries to look mutex one with a timeout.
So here is some code to do that. We are using a timed_mutex so we can have the time out.
I have added some sleeps and print messages so we can see what's happening.
And then we lock the first
mutex, we try to lock the second and we do that in a loop.
And then we have the other thread function, which is the same, but it locks mutex two first and then
tries to lock mutex one with a timeout.
And then the main function to launch the threads.
So here we are.
They're both busy apologizing to each other and nobody actually gets through the door.
How can we prevent this?
Well, the obvious way is to use a proper deadlock avoidance technique, for example, we could
use the scoped lock from C++17 or the unique lock with extra arguments and the global lock function from
C++11.
I will let you try that out for yourselves.
It is pretty straightforward.
Another way to avoid livelock is to assign different priorities to the threads. The operating system
actually does that for us, although it is not directly supported by C++.
When the scheduler is deciding which thread to allow to run next, it goes by the priority of the thread,
so the highest priority thread will get the most opportunities to run.
So threads with high priority will get the most opportunities to run.
And threads with the lowest priorities will get the least opportunities to run. They are more likely
to be sleeping, or when they do run, they are more likely to be interrupted.
We can call the native_handle member function of the thread object, and that will give us the data
which we need to pass as an argument to some operating system API, and that can set the priority of
the thread.
I will not show you how to do that, because it depends on the operating system.
Some issues you need to think about when you are doing that.
One of them is priority inversion.
We have a high priority thread, but it needs to wait for something that is a low priority thread is
doing. So it is going to stop what it is doing and it is going to wait until the low priority thread has
done what it needs.
However, because the low priority thread has low priority,
it keeps getting interrupted by other threads which are not relevant to what we are waiting for.
The high priority thread is actually running at the same speed as a low priority thread, so that is
why it is called priority inversion.
We have a high priority thread, which behaves like a low priority thread.
Another problem is convoying. We have a high priority thread which requires a lock, which is held by
a low priority thread.
So the high priority thread cannot get that lock until the low priority thread has released it.
And then if the high priority thread requires another lock, which is already held by the low priority
thread, then it has to wait until that runs, and so on.
So it keeps getting, er, bumping up against the low priority thread.
It is like having a sports car following a slow lorry up a hill [on a narrow road].
It wants to go faster, but it cannot.
And finally, resource starvation is a more general concept which covers deadlock and livelock and
some other things. It means that a thread cannot get the resources which it needs to run or to continue
running.
When we have deadlock and livelock, the thread cannot acquire a lock it needs.
We can have situations where the operating system has resource starvation, there is not enough system
memory to start a new thread, or the maximum number of threads that the operating system supports have already
been started.
With low priority threads, they may get starved of processor time. Because they are low priority, they
do not get to run very often. Good schedulers will try and introduce some element of fairness so that
low priority threads do get to run occasionally.
But they may not be able to run fast enough to do their required work.
Okay, so that's it for this video.
I'll see you next time.
But meanwhile, keep coding!