Hello again! In this video, we are going to talk about lazy initialization. The usual advice is to initialize
variables at the point where they are declared. This is known as "eager" initialization.
It is a good practice because for built-in types, it ensures they have a defined value.
And for class types, it ensures that they are properly set up and ready for use.
So there is no danger that we might accidentally use a variable that is not a well defined state.
However, there is an alternative, "lazy" initialization.
This means that a variable is not initialized
until the first time it is used.
This is mainly used when there is quite a bit of overhead involved in creating or initializing the variable.
For example, if we need to get data from a database or set up a network connection.
If they are paths through the program in which the variable is not used or if it is not actually convenient
to have that overhead at the point where it is declared, then you can declare it uninitialized and
initialize it later.
This is the traditional way to do it in C++.
We have a class of some type, it does not really matter what it does.
We have a global variable, which is a pointer to some instance of this class.
We give it the initial value null, to indicate that it has not been initialized.
And then before we use it, we check whether it has been initialized. If it is the first time and it is
not initialized then we initialize it. And then, once we know that it is safe to use it, we can do something
with it.
And this works fine in single threaded programs, but is it safe in multithreaded programs?
Well, I hope you considered the possibility of a data race.
So we have multiple threads which will access this, because they all need to check this value, and we
have threads which may modify them because one thread will need to write to the variable.
So we do have the potential for a data race.
So let's fix that by putting a mutex in.
So there we are, we have a mutex instance here and then we lock the mutex before we do the check.
And then once we get past the critical region in which we have potential conflict, then we unlock the
mutex. And that will work perfectly well.
But again, this might remind you of something.
This is the situation where we had multiple readers and few writers.
In this case, we only have one writer, which is the first thread that calls this.
So we need to lock the threads to prevent that thread from being interrupted.
But once the value has been initialized and we are just reading it, we do not need to lock it again.
So all these mutex lock() and unlock() calls are actually a waste of time once we get past that first
initialization.
The problem here is that we are going to all this trouble with lazy initialization to avoid unnecessary
overhead when we initialize this variable at some time.
But then we add lots more unnecessary overhead with all this locking.
The next attempt is that we only look the mutex if we need to.
So first we check the pointer, then we lock the mutex if we need to and initialize it.
Otherwise, we jump straight to the use of the variable.
So that means we only lock the mutex the first time when the value is being written to.
So is this thread-safe?
Well, no, still not quite.
We still have a data race. It is possible that the first thread can check ptr and then get interrupted,
and then another thread runs. It checks the pointer.
It gets the lock, initializes and releases the lock.
Then the first thread runs again, gets the lock and initializes the pointer again.
So we have initialized it twice, which is not what we intended to do.
So what we can do then is to check the pointer a second time.
This check is inside the lock, so we are the only thread that can be doing this check.
So if some other thread has come along and initialized the pointer in between these two statements,
then when we check it here, the test will fail and we do not create a second variable.
OK, so is this thread-safe?
And the answer, believe it or not, is that it is not thread-safe.
You may recall that when we were talking about the Singleton, I said there are actually two race conditions
and this is where it comes in.
The problem is that this is actually three separate operations, so let's try and find out what is going
on here.
When we call the new operator to create a variable on the heap, there are actually three separate things
that happen.
The first one is that we allocate the money on the heap and the program will make sure there is enough
memory for the object to be stored there.
Then we need to create an object in that memory, which is calling the constructor.
And then finally, we need to save the address of this memory that has been allocated.
So you may expect that they are done in that order, that the allocation is done first, then the constructor call
and then the store of the address.
Unfortunately, however, C++ allows lots of scope for reordering operations and this is one of the
situations where it allows it.
So it is quite possible that the program could allocate the memory and then save the address of that
memory and then go back and construct the object in this memory.
It is possible that the thread could be interrupted between these two operations, so the value of ptr
has been set, it is no longer null. Any other thread that checks that will think that the initialization
has been done.
However, the constructor call has not yet been done.
And then when the second thread goes ahead and accesses that memory, it will access an object that has
not been constructed and that will be very bad.
So we have a threat A, which is going through these steps. It is allocated the memory and it gets suspended.
So ptr has been set, but the memory does not contain any actual data. Then a thread B calls this function.
It tests the ptr to see whether it needs to acquire a lock.
Then it will see that ptr is not null
it will not try to get a look, it will jump straight to the call.
And then it is going to call a member function of an unconstructed object, and that is undefined behaviour.
So the problem is that thread A could come through here and it gets as far as this and then gets
suspended, when it has set ptr, but it has not created the object.
Then a second thread runs, it checks ptr, ptr is not null, so it jumps straight to this function call
even though ptr does not contain a properly constructed object.
By the way, this is known as double-checked locking. This is a very popular algorithm, but it does not work,
at least not the way that it has been written here.
There are various ways to address this.
One is to use a function called call_once, which does what the name suggests.
It ensures that a function is only called once.
It also guarantees that it is done in one thread and the thread that is doing the call cannot be interrupted
until the function call has completed.
To use that, we need to create a global instance of a once_flag variable, and then we pass that instance
and the function that wants to be called, to call_once.
So it will look like this.
We have our once_flag. This flag is used by the program to store synchronization data.
So there is quite a lot going on behind the scenes.
And then we call the function call_once, we pass this once_flag as the first argument and then, as
the second argument, we pass the function that we want to have called.
In this case, we just want to execute the call to new(), which sets the value of the ptr.
So this double-checked looking with call_once, is thread-safe, but it has less overhead than using a mutex.
There is actually another way of doing this, if you think back to the Singleton, then we solved that
by using a static variable.
And finally, just to confuse things even more, C++17 specified the order in which the operations
are performed in a [call to] new().
So the allocation is always done first, then the construction of the object and then storing the address
of the memory.
So there's no longer a race condition in the classic implementation of double-checked looking.
So we now have four ways to do lazy initialization in a thread-safe way. We can use the mutex as we did
at the beginning,
if we are not worried about the overhead. We can use this call_once
function to make sure the initialization code only gets called once.
We can use the classic double-checked locking algorithm with a compiler that supports C++17, and finally
we can make this a static local variable provided we do not need it anywhere else.
OK, so that's it for this video.
I'll see you later, but meanwhile, keep coding!