Hello again.
In this video, we are going to look at shared data initialization. There are various ways we can create
shared data.
We could use a global variable or a static variable, which is declared in the namespace scope.
And that could be shared by all the threads in the program, including main(). We could have a class member
which is declared static and that is potentially shared by all threads which execute a member function
of the class.
And then finally, we can have a local variable in a task function and we declare that variable static.
And this is shared by all threads which execute that function.
There are actually two different rules for initialization.
One is for local variables, which we will look at in a minute, but for everything else, the variable is initialized
when the program starts up.
And at that point, there is only going to be one thread running. main() has not even been called yet.
So there cannot be a data race because there are not any conflicting threads.
When we have a local variable, so we have a function with a static local variable, C++ says this variable
will be initialized the first time that the program executes this code.
And in a single threaded program, that is all very straightforward.
But what happens when we have threads?
I would like you to pause the video for a moment and think about whether there could be any issues with
this.
Just in case you have forgotten, here is the definition of a data race.
So we have potentially conflicting accesses.
We could have multiple threads accessing the shared local variable, and one or more of these threads could
be trying to initialize it.
So we have the usual potential for a data race. But do we actually get one?
In older versions of C++, there was no acknowledgement of the existence of threads, so the behaviour
was undefined.
In C++11, it actually specifies that only one thread can perform the initialization. If any other thread
tries to access the local variable while it is being initialized, it will be blocked until the first thread
has finished initializing it.
So this means that the initialization "happens before" any other access and therefore we do not get a data race.
Obviously, that only applies when we are initializing the variable.
If we modify it later on, then it is exactly the same as any other type of variable.
And we need to protect against a data race.
Moving away from built in types, a more interesting example of shared data is the Singleton class.
There is a famous book about design patterns, and if you ask people for an example of a design pattern,
they will say Singleton, even if they have never read the book or heard of any other design pattern.
A singleton is a class that is written in such a way that there can only be one global instance of it in the
program. You would use this if you need to have only one instance of something.
For example, if you have a class that writes to an audit trail, there is no point having different
instances writing to the same log file.
That just complicates things.
You would implement a Singleton class in C++ by deleting the copy and move operators, so that prevents
the program from creating a new instance and then you provide a global function which returns the instance
of the class.
This will check if the instance already exists.
If it does not exist, it will create it and initialize it and then return it.
If it already exists, then it just returns it.
So this is a classic 1990s style implementation of a singleton.
We have the class that is defined somewhere.
We have a global variable, which is a pointer to the Singleton instance.
And we initialize this with the null pointer to indicate that it is not pointing to a valid Singleton
instance.
This is a global variable.
So it's going to be initialized at runtime before any separate threads are started.
So there are no issues about data races with this assignment here.
Then we have a function which returns a pointer to the singleton.
This will check if the instance has been initialized.
If the variable single is equal to null pointer, then the instance has not been initialized, so it will
create it and return it and initialize it, otherwise it will just return it straightaway.
And if you have a single threaded program, it all works perfectly. However, if we have multiple threads,
then there is a data race and I would like you to pause the video again and try and work out where the
data race is.
OK, did you find it?
There are actually two data races in here, but the second one is rather subtle.
We will talk about it in another video.
But if you spotted that one as well, then put a gold star on your screen!
The race condition is in here. If we have multiple threads calling this function, then we have multiple threads
which are accessing "single" and the possibility that threads are modifying "single".
I have actually spared you the data race [definition]. I hope it's still fresh from the last time!
So what can we do about this? As it happens, the guarantees about initializing static local variables
in C++11 mean that it's very straightforward to write a function that returns a Singleton instance.
This is it.
Yes, all of it!
We don't have the global pointer anymore.
We just have a static instance, which is a local variable in the Singleton function.
And then instead of returning a pointer, we return a reference to it.
So how does this work?
The rules for initializing local static variables say that the first thread to execute this code will
initialize it and it cannot be interrupted until it has finished the initialization.
So by the time another thread runs, this single variable has already been initialized.
So the first time through, it is going to initialize this variable and return it. The second time through, it is just
going to return it.
So here is a Singleton instance. It is just a very trivial class.
I have deleted the copy constructor,
copy assignment operator, move constructor and move assignment operator.
These have private access, so in fact, they do not actually need to be deleted. Because they are private,
they cannot be called from outside the class. But putting equals delete means it is obvious that I
want these functions never to be called.
This, by the way, is a C++11 feature.
I have got a constructor, which is just a trivial one. It will print something out, so we can see if the
constructor has been called.
I also have a forward declaration for the function to get the Singleton instance.
That function is just the same as the one on the slide.
Then there is a main function. It starts up some threads.
The task function for the threads will just
call get_singleton() and then we are going to print out the address of this instance, which is returned
by the function,
so we can see whether it really is the same object.
OK, let's try that out.
So there we are, we get the constructor output once, so that looks as though the object has only
been created once,
and we get the same address.
(Obviously, we get the interleaving because the output hasn't been protected by a mutex)
Let's just run it once again, that is a slightly nicer version.
OK, so that is it for this video.
I will see you next time.
But meanwhile, keep coding!