Hello again.
In this video, we are going to look at shared mutexes.
So we now know how to use mutexes to make sure that only one thread can execute in a critical region
at any one time.
That is very useful, but occasionally it is a bit too restrictive.
Let's imagine that we have a situation
where we have some data which is accessed for reading very frequently, but only very rarely modified.
If we use the techniques we have learnt so far, this means that every time a thread wants to read this
shared data, it has to get an exclusive lock on it and no other threads can access it, even if it is
just to read it.
So this means if we have, say, 1000 threads which read the data and only one thread which writes
to it, then 999 times out of 1000, we are looking the mutex when we do not need to.
And that is going to have a big effect on performance.
On the other hand, on the occasional time when there is a thread which modifies the data, then we
want to make sure that all the reading threads are locked out to prevent a data race.
So we cannot just take the mutexes off.
If you were using C++11, there was not very much you could do about this, at least not using standard
C++.
C++14 provided a mutex which could be used for this and a type of lock.
C++17 improved the mutex by removing the timeout functions, which the C++14 mutex had.
So let's find out how all this works,
The C++17 shared mutex, which we are going to look at, is defined in the  header.
There are actually two different ways in which it can be locked.
The first one is exactly the same as every other mutex that we have looked at so far, which is to get
an exclusive lock.
If a thread has an exclusive lock on this mutex, then no other thread can acquire a lock until this
thread releases the lock.
There is also a shared lock. When a threat has a shared lock, any other thread can also acquire a shared
lock on the mutex.
It does not have to wait for this thread to release the lock.
If another thread wants to get an exclusive lock, it has to wait until all the threads which have shared
locks release them.
And also if the thread has an exclusive lock, then no one can get a shared lock until that is released.
To get an exclusive lock is exactly the same as the other mutexes, so we can use lock_guard, unique_lock
or scoped_lock as we wish.
This will give the thread exclusive access to the critical region.
Only one thread can access it. If another thread wants to access the critical region,
it will have to wait until this thread releases the exclusive lock.
There is also a shared_lock which provides shared access.
Any thread can share access to the critical region with other threads which also have shared locks.
If there is a thread which has an exclusive lock, then the thread will have to wait to acquire its shared lock.
So how would we use this in code?
We would create an instance of the shared mutex. We would create read and write task functions.
The write function will get an exclusive lock on the mutex, so only one thread can write to the shared data at
any one time.
The reader threads will get shared locks on the mutex so any thread can read the data provided that
no-one is writing to it.
So let's have a look at some code that does this. So here we are.
I have got a write task function.
This gets a lock guard on the mutex.
So this is going to acquire an exclusive look.
While this write task is executing its critical region, no other thread can access it.
The read test function takes a shared lock on the mutex, so we could have many threads executing this
read task at the same time. And instead of sharing data, I am just going to print out a number, which
depends on the threads.
I have included the shared_mutex header. In the main() function, I am creating lots of threads which read
and one thread which writes. When you want to create lots of threat objects, it is useful to put them
into a vector.
Then when you populate the vector, the thread objects cannot be copied, but they can be moved.
So this is going to transfer ownership of the underlying system thread from the thread object into
the vector element.
So I create some reading threads here, I create a writer thread, and then I create some more reading
threads.
And then finally I iterate over the threads and join each one.
I need to use the reference version of auto here because the thread objects cannot be copied.
Okay, so let's see how this works.
So we have some reading threads start up.
They all get a shared lock and they can all access the critical region.
The write thread gets an exclusive lock and now all the read threads which come afterwards have to wait.
And when - yes, there it is! - the write thread releases its look and then the other reading threads
can run.
And you will notice the output is slightly scrambled up.
OK.
Let's remind ourselves about the conditions for a data race.
I am going to keep displaying this slide until you see it in your dreams! Or perhaps that should be nightmares!!
So the condition for a data race is when we have:
two or more threads which access the same memory location and at least one of the threads modifies
the memory location.
So that is the case here.
We have a reading thread and writing thread.
These are safe only if the accesses are synchronized in some way.
Each access is made to happen before the next,
or the accesses are made atomically.
So how does using a shared mutex help us prevent a data race?
So we have these potentially conflicting reader and writer threads. The writer threat cannot get an exclusive
lock and execute the critical region until all the reader threads, which are currently accessing the
critical section, release their shared locks.
So this means that the accesses by these reader threads will happen before the access by the writer thread.
If the writing thread has an exclusive lock and reader threads want to get a shared lock, they cannot do that
until the writer has finished accessing the critical section and releases the exclusive lock.
So the access by the writing thread will happen before the access by these other reader threads.
So we have the reader and writer threads "happening before" the ones which could conflict. The accesses by
multiple reading threads do not have the happens before ordering, but that does not matter because they
do not modify the data, so they cannot conflict.
So we never have a situation in which a reader and a writer thread are executing the critical section
at the same time.
So there is no situation in which the reader and writer threads are interleaved.
OK, so that is it for this video.
I will see you next time.
But meanwhile, keep coding!