Hello there! In this video, we're going to talk about thread-local variables.
C++ supports variables which
are thread-local.
We use the thread underscore local keyword to declare a variable as being local to a thread.
So these are quite similar to static variables. The difference is, with a static variable, you get a
single instance which is shared by all the threads.
With a thread_local variable,
Each thread has its own instance.
We can declare thread-local variables anywhere that we can declare a static variable. We can declare them
at namespace scope, we can make them static data members of a class and we can make them local
variables in a function.
When they are at static and name space scope, they will be constructed at or before the first time they are
used in a translation unit.
And just to remind you, a translation unit is a source code file in which all the header files have
been included and preprocessed.
So that means they avoid the problems that can arise in Windows when you are sharing variables across
different translation units in a dynamic library.
Local variables, which are thread-local, are initialized in the same way as static local variables. There
will not be a data race, of course, because only one thread can access a thread-local variable.
Thread-local variables are destroyed when the thread function returns.
There is no guarantee about the order in which local variables are constructed, but they are destroyed
in the reverse order in which they were constructed.
One application of local variables: if we are using the C++11 features for random numbers, we can
arrange things so that each thread has its own access of a random number engine.
And if we do not seed the engine, or we use the same seed for all the engines, then that means that each
thread will generate the same sequence of random numbers.
And that's useful if you are testing. If you are not familiar with the C++11 random numbers, it is quite
different from the old rand() function from C. So we create an instance of the random number engine.
This has an overloaded function call operator, and every time you call that operator, you get
the next random number in the sequence.
Normally you use random numbers with a distribution which will scale the numbers.
In this case, we have a uniform distribution of real numbers which are doubles in the range from zero
to one.
So this avoids having to work out how to divide by RAND_MAX and add numbers and then worry about
whether you have introduced bias into the distribution.
This will always return uniformly distributed random numbers.
So in this case, we are creating the random number engine.
And then the distribution will also have a function call operator. Then every time we call that, we
give the number [engine] instance as the argument, and then that will get the next random number from the sequence
and it will scale it to fit into the distribution.
So we call it like that. We are going to call it 10 times, so it is going to generate ten random numbers
between zero and one.
I have got some code here which demonstrates this.
So this is the thread function from the slide.
I have got some headers.
I have also written a main function, which is going to create a thread and that will print out 10 random
numbers.
Then it creates another thread and prints out 10 numbers.
So let's see how that works.
So you can see that both threads are printing out the same random numbers.
The reason for this is this each thread has its own instance of the engine, which is not seeded.
So each thread is going to print out the first 10 numbers from the random engine's sequence.
Now, let's see what happens if we remove that.
So this is now just an ordinary global variable.
It is shared by all the threads.
So each time a thread calls it, it is going to get the next number from the sequence.
This time, the threads have different random numbers, so the first thread gets the first 10 random numbers,
then thread 2 is using the same random number engine.
So it gets the next 10 numbers from the sequence.
Before,  thread 2 was using its own instance of the random number engine, and that gave it the first 10 numbers of
the sequence.
OK, so that is it for this video.
I will see you next time, but meanwhile, keep coding!