Hello again.
In this video, we are going to look at data races. I am going to show you an example of a data race
and then discuss the kinds of problems that they can cause.
So we remember the definition of a data race?
It is when we have accesses from multiple threads which are not ordered or atomic.
So here is the code
that I am going to use to demonstrate this.
It is quite similar to the example in the last video.
We are going to have three threads which print a message to the screen.
In the last video, I was careful to make sure that the threads could not print to the screen at the
same time, by putting sleeps in.
And in effect, that means the threads run one after the other. In this case, I actually want the threads
to try to print to the screen at the same time.
To do that, I have broken up the print statement into separate outputs of each character. So the thread
could be interrupted between each of these function calls [to operator
There are three function calls as opposed to one, so that is three times as many opportunities to be interrupted.
And I have also put a sleep in here, which will give the scheduler more opportunities to interrupt threads
and let other threads run.
So let's see what happens when we run this.
That is an extremely boring example!
OK, this one is better.
So the threat that prints "abc" runs first, it gets to print "a" and "b", then it gets interrupted before it can
do its final output
operator call. Then the "xyz" thread and the "def" thread both run and print all their output.
And then the "abc" thread wakes up again and it is able to output the final character.
So one of the things about data races is that they are not easily reproducible.
And that does not look like a data race at all! So it's like undefined behaviour, not necessarily predictable
and it can look as though everything is working fine.
OK. There is another one. So I think you've got the idea by now.
This is one that I prepared earlier,
as the Children's TV program says.
So you can see here we had interleaving where the first thread prints "a"
and it gets interrupted, the second thread prints "d", the first thread runs again and prints "b", the
second thread runs again and prints "e"
and "f".
And then
the first thread can run and print "c". So the interleaving process: threads appear to run in between
other threads.
So we have the "abc" thread running here and the "def" thread appears to run in between what the "abc" thread
is doing.
And that is called interleaving.
This oval is meant to be the program, this squiggle is meant to be one of the threads and this is meant
to be another one of the threads.
So if you imagine this is the "abc" thread and this is the "def" thread, this thread gets to run prints
"a" to the screen and it gets interrupted.
Then this thread can run, it prints "d" on the screen.
Then it gets interrupted.
And this thread runs again, prints "b" and so on.
So we end up with this interleaved output.
So we had a data race. We have several threads which are trying to access the same location, in this
case, the output object cout. There was no ordering between the threads, so we did not have them
"happening before" each other.
And the access was not atomic. In our program, we saw interleaved output, but that was quite lucky, really.
iostream is specially designed
so nothing worse than that can happen, if you have threads trying to write to an iostream at the same time.
You can get much worse consequences. For example, the results of computations can be incorrect. The
program flow can be incorrect, so it does not execute in the way that it should do.
We can get torn writes and reads, which mean that data is corrupted. And we can get objects which
are not being properly constructed or destroyed.
So let's go through these. By the way, the code in these examples is deliberately bad.
I do not recommend
that you write code like this!
The reason I have done this is to demonstrate the problem in a very short, simple bit of code.
We have a thread function which is doing some calculations on a shared variable x. So it does one
calculation here, the statement to calculate a, and another one to calculate b. If the thread is interrupted
between these two statements and another thread runs and changes the value of x, then the value of b is
going to be calculated using a different value of x from the one that was used to calculate a.
So the results a and b are going to be inconsistent.
And this does not just happen between statements.
It can also happen within statements. As we saw in the print program where we have output operator
calls and threads could be interrupted between calling successive output operations.
For example, if we're squaring x, then adding two times x to it, and adding one, that is two multiplication
operations and two additions.
And the thread could be interrupted between any of those.
So when we are calculating x squared, we could use one value of x here. Then if we are interrupted
before doing the multiplication, then we could use a different value of x here.
Incorrect program flow. We are calculating a square root. We want to be careful and make sure that
the value is positive because it is an int and ints can have negative values.
And if we take the square root of a negative number, we get a runtime error.
So we test if it is safe to use x and then we take its square root.
If the threat gets interrupted between doing the test and doing the square root and another thread sets
the value of x to be negative, then we are going to get a run time exception here.
But how is that possible?
We checked the value of x, didn't we.
Incorrect program flow.
We have a switch statement where we call different functions, depending on the value of x. We want
to make sure that x is within range because our case statements go from zero to nine.
So we check the value of x before we go into the switch.
And - maybe you've guessed by now - if the thread gets interrupted between doing the check by some other
thread that changes the value of x, then this is not going to work as expected.
If it sets x to 10, then none of the cases will match and it will just jump over and out of the switch
statement.
And for bonus points, there is an even nastier bug hiding in here. Compilers are allowed to do lots
of things to the code to optimize it.
One of the common optimizations for a case statement is to convert it to a branch table.
The compiler will generate some code which creates an array, the indexes of this array will be the
case labels, and the elements will be pointers to the functions that get called.
If, for example, the value of x is zero, then the program will go to the element with index zero and
it will call the function in there, which will cause it to call a().
And the problem is, if we have an interruption which sets the value of x to 10, the program will go to the
element within the index 10, which is not actually part of the array, because the highest index is
nine, and it is going to execute the function there, which could be any arbitrary code.
So who knows what could happen then!
Torn writes and reads, These are actually very difficult to demonstrate on current hardware.
If you're using something like ARM or PowerPC from the 2000s, then there are some cases where this
could happen.
These are 32 bit systems, but they have instructions which can take 64 bit arguments.
So, for example, you can save a 64 bit integer.
The addresses where the integer gets saved can only store 32 bits, so this is done by splitting
the number into half. The first half gets written into one memory address and the second half is written into
the memory address next to it.
The problem occurs when we have two threads which are writing to that location at the same time, so
the first thread will write the first half of this number to the first address.
Then it gets interrupted. Another thread will run and write both halves of its number to the two addresses.
So it is going to overwrite what is in the first half of the address.
Then the original thread will start again.
It'll write the second half of its number into the second half of the address.
So that'll overwrite what the thread "B" just put there.
So we're going to end up with a number that has the first half of thread A's number [sic] and the second
half of thread B's number [sic].
It's as if you'd written down thread A's number and thread B's number on pieces of paper and then torn
them in half and swapped them around.
So we have the first half of A and the second half of B. Sorry, the first half...
So we have the first half of B and the second half of A.
And we can also have a torn read, which happens when a thread, which is reading, is interrupted by
another thread which is writing.
So the reading thread will get the first half of the number, then the writing thread will overwrite that
and put a different value in the second half of that number.
And then the reading thread will pick up that new value from the second half.
So it will be the number, which again is a mixture of two different values.
Improper construction. If we imagine a thread which is creating an object and it calls the object's
constructor. While it is doing that, it is interrupted by another thread, which is also calling a constructor
on the same memory location.
And that's going to give us a torn write.
If we imagine the constructor has several initialization statements and some of those get executed
by one thread and some of those get executed by another thread, we are going to have a torn
write.
And the object is going to be initialized with a mixture of values from each thread.
Another horrible bit of code!
We have a situation where we have a class with inheritance and in the base class, the base class will
push an instance of itself onto a vector of pointers to the base.
As you probably know, when you have a derived class object, that contains an instance of the base class
object and that base class object is created before the derived class constructor is called.
So if we call the derived class constructor, it'll call the base class constructor.
The base class constructor will push back a pointer to the partially constructed base object.
And then if some other thread accesses that element of the vector before the derived class constructor
has run, then it is only going to see a partially constructed object.
And finally, improper destruction. You probably know about the shared_ptr in C++11, which is a reference
counted object.
The idea is that every time a reference to the object is destroyed, a counter is decremented. When
the counter goes down to zero,
that means the last reference has been destroyed and then we can delete the object and its management
data.
So imagine we try to implement this ourselves.
Obviously, the real shared_ptr does not suffer from this.
It has been designed intelligently.
But if we try to write it ourselves and get it wrong, then something like this could happen.
We have an integer which is decremented, and then we check if it is equal to zero. In a threaded program,
we could have two threads which are destroying their reference at the same time.
And if one threat gets interrupted after doing the decrement, but before doing the check, then we
can have the situation where the reference count has the wrong value.
If the reference count is two, then one thread decrements it down to one and then it gets interrupted, then the next thread
will take it down to zero.
Then that thread will see the reference count equal to zero and the first thread, when it runs again, will also see that the
reference count is equal to zero.
So these deletions are done twice.
On the other hand, if the reference count is one initially, then the first thread will decrement it to zero,
then it gets interrupted.
The second thread decrements it to minus one, then both sides will see a value of minus one.
So this check fails and the deletion is not done.
So in fact, we have a memory leak.
So data races are pretty nasty things, how do you manage them?
The only real answer is not to allow them to occur in the first place.
As we have seen, they occur intermittently. It requires some kind of timing coincidence to actually
trigger bugs, and they're also sensitive to environment as well.
Sometimes they only occur under heavy load.
So the best way to deal with data races is to make sure they do not happen in the first place.
So if we think back to the definition of a data race where we have accesses from different threads,
we have accesses which are not ordered and we have accesses which are not atomic.
So to avoid a data race, you do the opposite of those.
So we make all the accesses in the same thread.
So do not share data between different threads unless it is absolutely necessary.
Or we can make the accesses "atomic", which we will look at later on in the course.
So we use shared data which can be accessed using so-called "atomic" operations, which can't be interrupted.
Or we can make each access happen before the next, so we impose some kind of ordering on how threads access
shared data, and we will be looking at that in the next section of this course.
Until then, keep coding!