Hello again.
In this video, we are going to start looking at things called "mutexes".
We saw in the last section that data races can occur when multiple threads try to access the same memory
location. And if we impose some sort of ordering on the threads as they access this location, then
we can avoid a data race.
And a mutex is one of the tools for doing that.
I am afraid this is rather a tasteless analogy, so I apologize to anyone who is offended by it.
So let us step away from computers for a moment and go to more domestic matters.
We have a situation where we want to impose a rule that only one person can access the bathroom
at a time.
So a common solution is to put a lock on the door and everyone who uses the bathroom has to agree on
a protocol.
If the door is unlocked, then you can lock it, access the bathroom, and then you unlock it so the
next person can access the bathroom. If the door is locked, then you have to wait until it becomes
unlocked.
In computer science, the bathroom would be regarded as a "critical section".
This means some part of the program that must be able to execute without other parts of the program
interfering with it.
The bathroom door lock would be called a mutual exclusion object or "mutex" for short.
And we have this protocol in which two or more users of a resource agree that they will use the mutex to
control access to it. So provided everybody plays by the rules,
the mutex will prevent more than one user accessing the resource and executing the critical section
at any one time.
The mutex is a data structure. It is a very simple object that just has two states: it is either locked
or unlocked.
The way this works in threaded programs where we have multiple threads trying to access a resource is that
we associate a mutex with the resource and a thread can only access the resource if the mutex is unlocked.
So you can imagine we have several threads which want to access the resource.
They try to get a lock on the mutex.
Only one of them can succeed.
So the first one there, thread A, will look the mutex and the other threads will have to wait until the mutex
is unlocked by thread A.
Meanwhile, thread A has exclusive access to the resource and it can execute its critical region without
being interrupted [by another thread executing the same code]
Then when thread A finishes executing its critical region, it will unlock the mutex. Then one of the other
threads will be able to lock the mutex and access the resource.
So this means that, by the time any of threads B, C, D, etcetera, gets to access the resource, thread A will have
completed its access.
So the access by thread A will "happen before" any access by the other threads.
So we have been able to impose some ordering on the threads, how they access the resource.
And that means we have avoided a data race.
One other aspect of mutexes, which is more significant than it may sound: if a thread modifies the
resource, then all the threads that run after it will see the result of that modification.
So, for example, if thread A changes the value of a variable and then thread B runs, thread, B will
see the variable that was set by thread A.
When C++ added multi-threading, it provided a mutex class.
This is in the  standard header.
When we create a mutex object, it must be outside any of  the thread [functions] that are going to use it, but
it must be visible to all those thread [functions].
This usually means that if we have thread functions which are global functions, then the mutex has
to be a global or a static variable.
If the thread functions are member functions of a class, then the mutex will usually be a data member of that class,
although it could still be a global or static variable.
There are three main functions that we are interested in.
The lock member function will try to lock
the mutex.
And this call will not return until the mutex has been locked.
So that is what is called a "blocking" call.
If a thread tries to unlock the mutex and some other thread has got the mutex lock on, then this thread is going
to be stuck waiting for the call to return, until the other thread unlocks it and the thread is able to get
the lock.
An alternative to that is the try_lock function, which will return immediately.
This returns a boolean.
If we have a lock on the mutex, the result is true.
Otherwise, the return value is false.
So that is useful if you do not want to wait an indefinite amount of time to get the lock. You could
do something else and then try again.
And then finally, the unlock member function, which does what you might expect.
It releases the lock
on the mutex.
I have rewritten the code from the previous video to use a mutex. I have included the mutex header. I have
created a global mutex instance because the thread function is a global function and then, here is the critical
region of the thread function.
And before that, I have put in a call to lock the mutex.
And then after that I unlock the mutex.
So when each thread goes into this loop, it is going to try to lock the mutex.
When the lock call returns, that will mean the thread has [the lock on] the mutex.
It will mean that no other thread can execute [this code] while this critical region is being executed and then
it will unlock the mutex afterwards.
So let's see how that works.
There we are. It looks perfect, but as we saw, that does not necessarily prove anything.
So let's run it a few more times
and it looks through that has....
And it looks as though this has fixed the problem.
So this is what is happening. If we go back to the diagram that we had before,  I have added these locks and the
mutex so this is meant to be the mutex and these are the threads which are locking and unlocking it.
So thread one gets to run, it gets a lock on the mutex, and while thread one has a lock on the mutex,
no other thread can have a lock.
So thread one gets to write "abc" without being interrupted.
Then when it has finished, it unlocks the mutex, then some other thread can lock the mutex.
That thread can run one without being interrupted and that can write "def".
So we are going to get the proper output on the screen.
So that means that the output is no longer scrambled up.
We still have interleaved ordering because the threads can be scheduled to run in any order, but each
each thread's output is separate from the others.
It is not mixed up.
We have imposed a "happens before" relationship on the threats as they access the critical region, which
means they cannot interfere with each other.
Usually when we are using mutexes with data, we encapsulate them inside a class.
So, for example, if you want to have a vector, which is thread safe, we could create a class
which has a vector as a member and a mutex as another data member.
And then we have member functions which just forward to the vector's member functions, but with a lock, so
for example, when we call push_back on our thread safe class, this will get a lock on this mutex.
Then when the thread has looked the mutex, it will call the push_back member function on the vector and
then it will unlock it.
So this means that only one thread
can modify the vector at any one time.
Obviously, this is a rather simplistic example.
The mutex is an example of acquire and release semantics. When we lock the mutex, we acquire exclusive
access to the data it protects and to the critical region.
When we unlock the mutex, it releases the exclusive access to the data and it will also release the
results of any modification made to that data.
So the next thread which locks the mutex will acquire the results of that modification.
So these are acquire and release semantics are what imposes the ordering on the accesses to the variable.
There is no data race and the data will always be in a consistent state.
So we mentioned try_lock() before. This is typically how you use it. You have a loop in which you
keep calling try_lock().
If it does not get the lock, then this returns false and then you can do something else, and then
try again a bit later.
Then if the call does succeed, then it will return
true.
And you can carry on and do what... You can execute your critical region.
So you keep trying to get the lock in a loop until you succeed.
I have got some code which demonstrates this.
We just have the usual thread boilerplate at the top.
We have a mutex which both these threads are trying to lock.
Thread one will lock it immediately and then sleep for 500 milliseconds. Thread two will first
sleep and then try to get the lock.
It is going to keep trying to get the lock in a loop until it eventually succeeds.
At some point, thread one will wake up, it will unlock the mutex, and then thread two will get
the lock, this try_lock() call will succeed and the thread will jump out of the loop and execute its
critical region.
The main function just launches the threads and joins on them.
Nothing very exciting
there.
So we see task one and two both try to get the lock. Task one gets it straight away.
So by the time task two tries to get the lock, it's already been taken, it cannot get it, so it
sleeps and it tries again, sleeps, tries again, sleeps, and eventually task one releases the lock
and task two can get the lock.
Okay, so that's it for this video.
I'll see you next time.
But meanwhile, keep coding!